Hi, I'm Adam McFarland here on the Sunno
Music Team and welcome back to our
channel. Hopefully by now you had a
chance to dig into some of our past
videos and you know how to better do
things like generate songs layer by
layer, how to generate individual vocals
or instruments directly into Studio or
even how to upload your own audio into
Studio. In this video, we're going to
focus on how to edit and mix inside of
Studio. I'm going to cover stem
separation, adding effects, removing
effects, and so much more. Let's get
into it. First, I want to just show you
the original track.
>> Already hearing a couple of things that
I think we could change to make this a
little bit stronger, but strong start.
>> The first step in this process was stem
separation, which is the process by
which you split your audio into all its
component parts. different instruments,
different vocals, all the things that
make your song your song. You can do
stem separation other places inside of
Sunno, but for the purposes of this
video, we're going to do it right here
inside of Studio. Here's how. First,
you're going to select your track and
then rightclick that track and scroll
down to get stems. You can then choose
the advanced split option and type in
the specific stems that you want to
extract. I'm going to select synth,
bass, drums. Let's get some vocals. And
then we're going to extract. This may
take a little while, but trust me, it's
worth it. When the stems are generated,
I can audition the different versions
and then choose my favorite version, or
I can regenerate to extract them again.
I now have an option to either download
those stems in the form of an MP3, a lab
file, or even MIDI files. But in this
particular case, because I would like to
do some more with them inside of Suno
Studio, I'm just going to insert them
all into Sunno. Let's take a listen to
some of these stems to see how they
turned out.
First, our drums.
I actually really like that. That muted
kick sounds pretty dope.
>> Morning start till the caffeine hits a
while. No.
>> If you combine all the stems together
here. Here's our full song.
As you can see, by separating the stems,
I can actually create a more precise
mix. Not only can I change the volumes,
but I can also repeat sections. I can
cover instruments or even make new
generations. Okay, so for the purposes
of this video, we've actually jumped
forward a little bit. You'll notice that
in this new version, we've added in some
vocal generations. We've added in some
new instruments and even played around
with the arrangement a little bit so
that this song feels a bit more
complete. I want you to take a listen to
this song because you can hear some of
those changes that we've made before we
talk about how we made them.
follow.
Reckon I'll just stay here
by the window
waiting for the sky fall.
Now that we've heard the full song,
let's take a deep dive into how we were
able to get to this version of this
song.
First thing I hear is I think on my lead
vocal, I'd like to add a little bit of
compression and EQ. So, here's the dry
version without anything.
>> Now, I'm going to add in a compression
effect. And also,
let's play with the EQ. You can actually
make changes in real time and hear how
it sounds.
>> Take off some bottoms and I'll go there.
>> All right. I think I like how that
sounds. was able to alter my compressor,
increasing my threshold, and also I took
some of the bottom end off of the EQ,
adding a little bit on the top shelf.
Let's hear how it sounds inside of the
mixing.
>> I really like how that sits on top of
the mix, kind of calling a little bit
more attention to the vocal. Let's also
take a listen to this whirly. And I can
actually loop so that I'm only listening
to this portion of the whirly. In this
case, I think I'm going to add a little
bit of reverb. Let's hear how it sounds
currently.
Let's add a little bit of reverb. And
let's see how this sounds with the stock
reverb. And like I said before, you can
actually make changes in real time and
hear how it's going to sound.
Oo, I like that.
I think it sounds very ethereal, kind of
like otherworldly, which plays really
well with the rest of this mix. So,
let's hear how it sounds in the mix.
Okay, so that's how you add effects in
Suno. But sometimes you want to do the
opposite and you want to remove the
effects that get generated with your
audio. Here's how you do that. I have
soloed currently the guitar line. And
when I listen to this guitar line, I
think I hear a little bit of compressor,
maybe even a little bit of reverb. And
let's say, for example, I don't like how
this sounds. Take a listen.
Fortunately for me, within Sunno Studio,
I can actually remove effects, even the
effects that were a part of the original
generation. I simply select the track,
rightclick, and scroll down to remove
effects. Tuno is then going to give me
two track lanes that are filled with a
version of this guitar that has the
effects removed. Now we can see in lane
three and lane four two versions of this
guitar that are now labeled dry. Let's
hear how they sound.
That one sounds pretty good dry. Let's
take a listen to the second option.
Yo, I'm pretty pleased with how both of
those turned out. So, I'm going to
select the first one. If I would like to
input either of these tick links, I can
select the arrow here at the top. Let's
hear it inside of the mix.
Love it. Okay, so I was able to remove
the effect and make this super dry. But
if I wanted to add more reverb in or if
I wanted to alter any additional
effects, I could simply do that by
adding a track effect. Let's hear this
with a little bit of reverb that I've
added down.
Brand new to Studio 2.0 are two pretty
similar features, automation and clip
fades. To apply a clip fade, grab the
fade icon and drag it from one end of
the clip or select a section of the clip
that you'd like to fade and then use the
keystroke CtrlF. Take a listen.
Automation can be applied to almost any
parameter over the entire duration of
the track, not per clip. If I want to
automate any parameter within my
effects, I simply rightclick on the knob
that I'm looking to automate, click the
word automate, and then I'm able to make
individual markers with which I can make
very particular changes to how this
reverb shows up within my guitar line.
And just for the sake of demonstration,
I'm going to make some pretty dramatic
changes in the reverb here. Let's hear
what we got.
All right, that concludes this video on
editing and mixing in Suno Studio 2.0.
Thank you guys so much for joining in.
We want to make sure that everyone gets
super educated on how to use this
incredible tool. So, please go check out
some of our other videos. Hop in the
comments, let us know what you want to
see next. Thank you so much. I'm Adam
and this concludes our video. See you on
the next one.